## **CARLOS JOHN MAQUEDA**

930 Arlington St. Houston, TX 77008 1 (865) 296-0942 maqueda.cj@gmail.com

### PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

Large breadth of experience in the Energy Industry primarily focused in the areas of quantitative analysis and forecasting, project planning and management, capital budgeting, and optimization. Shaping strong working relationships, managing work streams across multiple countries and organizations, excelling in highly stressful and ambiguous environments, as well as embracing and quickly tackling new challenges have all been building blocks in my career's advancement.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

### MOTIVA ENTERPRISES, LLC

Houston, TX USA

# **Marine Commercial Freight Analyst**

May 2018 – Current

Accountable for analysis of marine freight market, commodities trade markets, micro and macroeconomic environments, and other relevant variables to forecast future freight rates. Responsible for the development of new analytics, models, and simulations to drive cost-effective charting of vessels to positively impact Motiva STL's P&L.

- Analyze historical freight data, supply/demand indicators, and key variables to create future forecasts for Traders & Charterers to adequately plan freight costs/impact.
- Publish weekly, monthly, and quarterly freight rate forecasts designed to support chartering decisions and deliver competitive advantage.
- Develop KPIs and track freight performance/variance against forecast.
- Design and maintain freight analytics dashboards and distribute management information reports
- Created a marine freight forecasting model to calculate expected marine freight market prices, using published "WorldScale" rates, increasing the likelihood of securing below market chartered marine transport costs.

#### MOTIVA ENTERPRISES, LLC

Houston, TX USA

### **Demurrage Analyst**

June 2017 – May 2018

Reported directly to the Motiva Marine Manager. Evaluated and prepared demurrage and ancillary claims payable to ship owners or receivable from third parties.

- Assessed intercompany demurrage charges on Motiva time-chartered vessels; negotiated and settled demurrage claims, delivered ~\$1.3M in value capture over a one-year period.
- Analyzed charter parties and cargo contracts to determine demurrage payable to ship owners on cargoes purchased on delivered basis.
- Scrutinized charter parties and contracts for free on board (FOB) and delivered cargo sales to determine demurrage billable to third parties.
- Monitored demurrage account receivables to identify delinquent payments.
- Provided root cause analysis of demurrage events and support for demurrage-related commercial initiatives.

## ORION PROJECT SERVICES, LLC

Houston, TX USA

## **Supply Chain Operations Project Analyst**

November 2016 – June 2017

Worked for the Supply & Logistics General Manager at Motiva Enterprises LLC. Developed a process/system for inventory management optimization to maximize net margin, by-terminal, through existing sales channels.

- Created an optimization model to consider supply/demand statistical variability to optimize system throughput while maximizing net margin, minimizing safety stock requirements, and maintaining terminal customer service reliability.
- Designed a marine logistics transportation calculation model to forecast expected voyage costs for multiple marine vessel trips, ensuring crude/crude products trade deals account correctly for all probable marine transport costs.

#### ROYAL DUTCH SHELL

Houston, TX USA

## **Integrated Activity Planner, Latin America Venture**

January 2014 – November 2015

Reported directly to the General Manager for the Latin America Venture. Responsible for capital budget allocation (~\$400M) for business planning cycles. Established short to medium-term execution plans, to ensure successful completion of the Argentina and Colombia operations plans.

• Managed operational activity execution against baseline schedule and forecasted costs (using P6 and/or MS Project), tracked actual performance on schedule and cost against agreed upon management KPIs.

- Delivered optimized business plan to meet 50% mid-year CAPEX budget reduction (e.g. ~\$400M down to ~\$220M). Plan delivered original business targets (production and revenue) with half the capital investment.
- Worked closely with Finance to ensure accurate and timely monthly, quarterly and year-end latest estimates and closings within \$400M CAPEX budget (~\$220mln revised budget).
- Created and implemented a risk-based schedule which generated a reliable probabilistic schedule to meet business plan targets and delivered over ~\$30M of unused drilling capital investment back to the organization.
- Coordinated the "Management of Change" process; performed analysis to ensure decision quality, and composed report detailing the approved changes and their expected impact(s) to ensure proper decision implementation.

ROYAL DUTCH SHELL Houston, TX USA

### **Integrated Activity Planner, Arrowhead Asset**

December 2012 - December 2013

Reported directly to the General Manager for the Arrowhead Asset. Coordinated cross-discipline alignment on strategies for drilling and completions to deliver targets within \$312M CAPEX budget.

- Administered the Operations Plan to deliver maximum production safely, on time, and on budget.
- Introduced probabilistic scheduling to the asset, ensuring a more accurate forecast of achievable business plan targets and the appropriate capital investment allocation.
- Evaluated schedule vs. baseline forecast, provided impact analysis, and recommend alternatives for delivery.
- Proposed and coordinated a well abandonment strategy that reduced well abandonment costs by \$2.8M, or a 45% overall
  decrease in the well abandonment budget.
- Coordinated a well delivery workflow redesign (technical limit workshop) which delivered a reduction in cycle time by 32%, ~\$810K cost savings/lateral well.

ROYAL DUTCH SHELL Houston, TX USA

## **Human Resources Account Manager/Analyst**

March 2010 – December 2012

Supported VP of Onshore Exploration for the Americas and the Commercial, Supply and Distribution General Manager as a member of both Sr. Leadership Teams. Served as HR advisor on employee issues, provided guidance and directed all aspects of employee relations for over 200 professional staff.

- Coordinated HR responsibilities with International Human Resource Partners (e.g. Argentina, Brazil, Canada, and Colombia) supporting the Exploration business.
- Managed four Affirmative Action Plans; created structured diversity plans by business to progress and support gap closure for minority and female staffing targets.
- Collaborated on an investigation to determine the root cause and future preventative measures of an environmental incident with potential loss of asset and working capital valued at ~\$15M.
- Implemented a consolidated and standardized pay schedule for hourly wages resulting in an estimated value capture of ~\$33M back to the SOPUS business and ~\$55M back to Motiva annuitized over a 30-year period.
- Performed market wage analysis for five collective bargaining agreements; ensuring wage targets were met and competitive pay levels were maintained.
- Coordinated the resourcing process, enabling cross business moves to enhance talent development and improve technical capabilities throughout Downstream businesses.
- Managed US work visa process for the Upstream Americas Business, ensuring over 100 visa cases in 2012 were completed with no delay or work interruption.

EXXONMOBIL Houston, TX USA

## **Human Resources Internship**

May 2009 - August 2009

Completed a summer internship with ExxonMobil Development Company. Managed all employment related issues, interpreting and applying organizational policy, and delivering successful project completion.

- Developed and implemented non-exempt training program for an approximately 200 administrative assistants to steward career development and advancement.
- Created new-hire feedback mechanism for short service employees to influence the continuous improvement of HR staffing services and processes through timely feedback.
- Managed the Summer Engineering Intern Program; planned, budgeted, and coordinated all summer internship activities and events for 37 interns.
- Facilitated annual employee performance evaluation and ranking meeting for a 75-employee functional group; collaborating with managers on performance management including goal setting, feedback and appraisal.
- Analyzed and recommended changes to the existing alcohol and drug testing processes to establish a structured and
  efficient program and ensure compliance with legal requirements.

#### AMERICAN COTTON GROWERS

Littlefield, TX USA July 2007 – July 2008

### **Special Projects Manager/Management Trainee**

Reported to the Quality Control Manager for a textile manufacturing plant. Developed, monitored, and evaluated projects designed to improve quality control throughout the production process.

- Supervised "Yarn", "Dye", and "Slashing" departments, serving as front line supervisor for up to 30 employees.
- Recommended and coordinated changes to workflow process that contributed to a ~22% increase in production.
- Developed LEAN process of "Greige" cloth testing to improve Quality Control standards. Statistically evaluated shade consistency denim goods, delivering predictions at a high statistical correlation.
- Formulated a cold-water wash cycle to meet eco-friendly customer demands.

#### **EDUCATION**

MOORE SCHOOL OF BUSINESS, University of South Carolina **Master of Human Resources**Darla Moore Fellowship
4.0 GPA

Columbia, SC USA December 2009

**CARSON-NEWMAN UNIVERSITY** 

Bachelor of Science in Business Management
Carson-Newman Outstanding Business Management Student

Jefferson City, TN USA May 2007

**LANGUAGES** Native tongue is English, fluent in Spanish

ACTIVITIES Continuing Education, Writing, Trail Running, Rock Climbing, Cooking, Reading, Camping, Skiing, Hiking